Guide to the Charles James Hendley Papers TAM.109
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Charles James Hendley Papers
1913-1962
1930-1960
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Hendley, Charles J.
Hendley, Edith Di Pasquale, Dr
TAM.109
18.75 Linear Feet in 18 record cartons, one manuscript box, one shared box and one oversize folder in a shared box.
Charles James Hendley (1881-1962) was a teacher, education reform advocate, political activist and union leader. A member of the Teachers Union of the City of New York from 1921 until his death, he served as its president from 1935-1945. The Charles J. Hendley Papers give a glimpse into his personal life and document his career, his political activities and his varied interests. The collection also provides a detailed look at the Teachers Union of the City of New York, tracing its history, internal and external conflicts, changing affiliations, and its efforts to bring about school reform as well as higher wages and better working conditions for its members. Correspondence, meeting minutes, financial and administrative documents, memoranda, newsletters and a significant amount of Hendley's editorials and other writings are included in the collection. The materials document educational issues of the 1930s, 40s and 50s; the impact of the Depression and World War II on New York City's schools; the relationship of the teachers with other unions, the civil rights movement, Popular Front political organizations and the American Labor Party; and threats to academic freedom from the Rapp-Coudert Committee investigations in the early 1940s and the post-war red scare which led to the harassment and firing of some of New York's teachers. Finally, there is a variety of publications, pamphlets, photographs and ephemera to provide additional historical context.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
The records are arranged into six series, two of which have been further arranged into subseries. This collection is arranged alphabetically.
Series I: Personal Papers, 1914-1962
Series II: Writings and Notes, 1914-1962
Subseries IIA: Writings, 1914-1962
Subseries IIB: Notes, Drafts and Fragements, 1930-1962
Series III: Teachers Union of New York Files, 1925-1962
Subseries IIIA: Teachers Union of NYC, American Federation of Teachers (AFT), Local 5, 1925-1941
Subseries IIIB: Teachers Union of NYC, Unaffiliated (After Expulsion from AFT), 1941-1943
Subseries IIIC: Teachers Union of NYC, Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO), Local 555, 1943-1950
Subseries IIID: Teachers Union of NYC, United Public Workers of America (UPWA), 1950-1952
Subseries IIIE: Teachers Union of NYC, Independent, 1953-1962
Subseries IIIF: Teachers Union of NYC - Organizing, Educational Policy, Professional Development and Political Action Groups, 1936-1961
Series IV: Academic Freedom Material, 1928-1961
Series V: Subject Files, 1914-1962
Series VI: Photographs, 1913-1959
Folders are arranged alphabetically within the following five series:
Missing Title
Series I: Personal Papers, 1914-1962.
Series II: Writings and Notes, 1914-1962.
Series III: Teachers Union of the City of New York Files, 1925-1962.
Series IV: Academic Freedom Material, 1928-1961.
Series V: Subject Files, 1914-1962.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Dr. Edith Di Pasquale Hendley, 2004. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2004.018 and 2004.019.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
The following archival collections contain material relating to the Teachers Union of New York City, academic freedom and other areas of interest to Charles Hendley:
Sam Wallach Papers (TAM 241)
Irving Adler Papers (TAM 273)
Henry Foner Papers (TAM 254)
Printed Ephemera Collection of Trade Unions (PE 001)
Oral History of the American Left: Radical History Collection (OH 002)
Frederic Ewen Audiotape and Videotape Collection (OH 052) This collection contains more than 30 interviews of teachers affected by the investigations of the Rapp-Coudert Committee.
Records of the United Federation of Teachers (WAG 022) Included within this collection are records of two predecessor unions, the Teachers Union of New York City and the Teachers Guild.
Rabinowitz, Boudin, Standard, Krinsky and Lieberman Legal Files (TAM 287)
Biographical Note
Charles James Hendley (1881-1962) was a teacher, education reform advocate, political activist and union leader. A member of the Teachers Union of the City of New York (Teachers Union of NYC) from 1921 until his death, he served as its president from 1935-1945.
Born in North Carolina on June 4, 1881, Hendley was the son of Alvis Francis Hendley, a section foreman on the Southern Railway who was a pioneer in organizing the maintenance-of-way men on the southern railroads. After attending local schools, he graduated from the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill in 1905. He taught for several years in small towns in North Carolina then moved north in 1915 and taught in New Jersey and Pennsylvania before coming to New York. In 1919 he helped organize a local of the American Federation of Teachers in Paterson, New Jersey, and in 1920, worked for the State Federation of Labor in Pennsylvania, teaching labor classes in Bethlehem, Reading and Lancaster. Once in New York, he taught labor classes for Local 3 of the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers and for a Wall Street local of telegraphers.
Hendley earned a masters degree at Columbia University and taught history and economics at George Washington High School in Manhattan from 1921 until 1946. A member of the Teachers Union of NYC, he served as its treasurer from 1922 through 1932 then became president in 1935 and held that position until just before his retirement from teaching.
In 1940, Hendley appeared before the Rapp-Coudert Committee. Although under the threat of arrest and probable dismissal from his teaching position, he defied the Committee, refusing its request to turn over the Teachers Union membership list. In January of 1941, however, at the behest of the Executive Board, on advice of union counsel, he complied with the Committee's demands.
After his retirement, Hendley continued his association with the Union serving on the Executive Board, as a member of the Educational Policies Committee and as Director of the Teachers Union Institute. In 1946, he became a field representative of the National Teachers Division of the United Public Workers of America (UPWA/CIO) and held that position until 1948. From his early years as a teacher, Hendley had been a member of the Socialist Party, resigning in 1938. He later grew closer to the Communist Party, apparently joining the Party in the late 1940s, but maintaining his oppostion to totalitarianism and authoritarianism in all forms.
In addition to his work with the Union, Hendley was active in the American Labor Party, running for State Senate (28th District, Bronx) in 1948 and for Congress (25th Congressional District) in 1950. In his later years he was a stockholder and served as Secretary-Treasurer of Publishers New Press, Inc., publisher of The Daily Worker. In that capacity he was called before the Senate Internal Security Committee in 1952 and also before a Grand Jury inquiry in 1962, consistently restating his belief in civil liberties for adherents of all political ideologies.
He remained active in his support of educational reform and other progressive causes. He wrote many articles, essays and letters to the editor; organized lectures; maintained throughout his life a keen interest in the political and cultural events of the day; and never lost his enthusiasm for learning.
Charles Hendley married Okla Dees of Grantboro, North Carolina, in 1916. They had two sons, Charles and Daniel.
- - - - - - -
The history of the Teachers Union of the City of New York was marked by controversy and changing affiliations. Organized in 1916 as Local 5 of the American Federation of Teachers (AFT), it began its long struggles on behalf of civil liberties, increased salaries, reduced classroom size, tenure for teachers, improved pensions and increased state aid to education. By 1925, however, organized political factions began appearing within the local's ranks and controversy over the Communist leanings of several of the factions culminated in a major crisis in 1935. The leadership petitioned the national office to investigate the local and hoped that the findings would allow them to reorganize without the Communist elements. This plan failed to gain adequate support from the AFT National Convention and, as a result, eight hundred dissatisfied members left Local 5 to join a newly organized, independent Teachers Guild. Charles Hendley, as a Socialist, was seen as a unifying figure when, in 1935, he took over the presidency of Local 5 and significantly expanded its membership.
Conflicts and disagreements continued however, and subsequent efforts to revoke Local 5's charter were finally successful in 1941. Although unaffiliated, the union continued to operate, initially attempting to rejoin the AFT but, eventually, in September of 1943, uniting with the State, County, Municipal Workers of America (SCMWA), a CIO union, as Local 555. In 1946, SCMWA allied with the United Federal Workers of America to become the United Public Workers of America (UPWA); the teachers continued as UPWA Local 555. In 1950, the UPWA was expelled from the CIO for alleged Communist domination; the Teachers Union of NYC withdrew from the UPWA in 1952. After twelve years as an independent organization, the Teachers Union of NYC was dissolved with the recommendation that its members join the the United Federation of Teachers (UFT), which had become the official collective bargaining agent for the City's teachers. The UFT had been formed as a result of the merger of the Teachers Guild with the Committee of Action through Unity (CATU) and strengthened after the first successful teachers' strike in New York City (May 1960.)
Sources:
Zitron, Celia Lewis, The New York City Teachers Union 1916-1964 (Humanities Press, 1968).
Scope and Content Note
The Charles James Hendley Papers give a glimpse into his personal life and document his career, his political activities and his varied interests. The collection also provides a detailed look at the Teachers Union of the City of New York, tracing its history, internal and external conflicts, changing affiliations, and its efforts to bring about school reform as well as higher wages and better working conditions for its members.
Correspondence, meeting minutes, financial and administrative documents, memoranda, newsletters and a significant amount of Hendley's editorials and other writings are included in the collection. These materials document educational issues of the 1930s, 40s and 50s; the impact of the Depression and World War II on New York City's schools; the relationship of the teachers with other unions, the civil rights movement, Popular Front political organizations and the American Labor Party; and threats to academic freedom from the Rapp-Coudert Committee investigations in the early 1940s and the post-war red scare which led to the harassment and firing of a number of New York's teachers. Finally, there is a variety of publications, pamphlets, photographs and ephemera to provide additional historical context.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragile nature of the originals, Series III.A. General Meeting Minutes and Membership Meeting Minutes in box 19 are accessible on microfilm only in the Tamiment reading room: Call Number R-7435 and R-7435A.
Correspondence.; Articles.; Publications (documents); Anti-communist movements.; Organization files.; Clippings files.; Card files.; Photographs.; Academic freedom |z United States.; Education -- New York (State) -- New York.; Financial records; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Socialism.; Teachers -- Workload -- New York (State) -- New York; Labor movement.; Communism and education -- New York (State) -- New York; Notebooks.; Communism -- United States.; Notes.; Speeches.; Drafts (documents); Minutes (administrative records); Antinuclear movement.; Political persecution -- Teachers and educators.; World War, 1939-1945.; Civil rights.; Race discrimination.; Newspaper columns.; New York (N.Y.); Economics.; American Labor Party of the State of New York; Teachers Guild; American Federation of Teachers; American Federation of Teachers. Local 5 (New York, N.Y.); Rapp-Coudert Committee; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); New York (State). Legislature. Joint Legislative Committee to Investigate the Educational System of the State of New York; Teachers' Union of the City of New York; Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley; Schappes, Morris U. (Morris Urman), 1907-; Hendley, Edith Di Pasquale, Dr
- Series I: Personal Papers, 1914-1962; 308643
  Scope and Content Note
  Directly related to Charles Hendley's personal life, this series includes biographical sketches; correspondence; financial documents; several items from his student days at Columbia University; and a quantity of material documenting his teaching career such as class record books, licenses, teaching appointments, reviews and ratings, and a First Assistants' Exam in Economics. Several personal statements of particular importance are also included - one concerning his decision not to run for re-election as President of the Teachers Union of NYC and another explaining why he joined the Communist Party.
  - Biographical Information, 1937-1961; 308644 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Columbia University: Registration Book (1911-1916), 308645 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Columbia University: "A Review of a Course in Intellectual History", 1914; 308646 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1921-1940; 308680 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1946; 308681 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1952; 308682 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1962, undated; 308683 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Family, 1914-1962, undated; 308684 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Family - Okla Hendley's Illness, 1946, 1949; 308685 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley and Foster, William Z. (Letters To), 1948; 308686 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Greeting Cards, 1940-1962, undated; 308687 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Job Search after Retirement, 1946; 308688 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Resignation from Socialist Party, 1938; 308689 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Decision Not to Run for Re-election as President of Teachers Union, [1945]; 308690 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hendley Testimonial Dinners, 1940, 1945; 308691 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hendley Testimonial Dinners: Testimonials, [1945]; 308692 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Membership and Business Cards, 1922-1946, undated; 308693 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Music Card File, undated; 308694 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Personal Finances, 1921-1948; 308695 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Personal Finances, 1951-1954, undated; 308696 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Personal Finances: New York State Income Tax, 1924-1937; 308697 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Personal Finances: War Ration Book, undated; 308698 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Photographs (Photocopies), 1941-1959, undated; 308699 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Study of Russia and the Russian Language, 1948-1955, undated; 308700 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Teacher Retirement System: Hendley Participation, 1924-1948; 308701 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Teachers Union, CIO, Local 555: Lifetime Membership Plaque, 1947; 308702 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Teaching Career: Appointments, 1924-1943; 308703 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Teaching Career: Class Record Books, 1933-1935; 308704 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Teaching Career: Early Interest in Improvement of Teaching Conditions, especially Pupil Load, 1923-1930; 308705 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Teaching Career: First Assistant's Exam in Economics, 1929; 308706 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Teaching Career: Licenses, 1921-1924; 308707 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Teaching Career: Review and Ratings, 1927-1943; 308708 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Teaching Career: Sabbatical Leave, 1936, undated; 308709 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Teaching Career: Tests, 1932, 1940-1945, undated; 308710 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Teaching Career: Various Materials, 1914-1946, undated; 308713 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Teaching Career: Various Materials, undated; 308714 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Various Items of Personal Interest, 1937-1952, undated; 308715 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Why I Enrolled in the Jefferson School", 1951; 308716 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Why I Joined the Communist Party" (handwritten draft), [1949]; 308717 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series II: Writings and Notes, 1914-1962; 308719
  - Subseries IIA: Writings, 1914-1962; 308720
    Subseries IIA of Hendley's writings includes articles, book reviews, lectures, press releases, letters to the editor and editorials and President's Columns written while he led the Teachers Union of NYC. The primary focus of these writings is on educational policies and reform; union efforts concerning salaries, class size, and working conditions; state and federal aid to schools; and academic freedom issues. Among other topics are the Civil War in Spain, the Cuban revolution, the Communist Party and socialism in the United States. Much of this material is in the form of typescripts.
    - "Academic Freedom under Big Business", 1953; 308721 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Argument for Full State Aid for Schools", 1941; 308722 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Book Reviews, 1946-1947, 1951-1952; 308723 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Budget and Salary Issues: Various, 1932-1949, undated; 308724 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - The Case of Local Five (bulletin), 1940; 308725 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Catholic Hierarchy's Challenge to American Institutions": with Submission Correspondence, 1947-1948; 308726 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Challenge to Youth", undated; 308727 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Children and Politics" (Partial, Annotated), [1953]; 308728 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Children and Politics" (Partial, Annotated), undated; 308729 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "Class Bias in American Public Schools", undated; 308730 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "Classroom Teacher's Responsibility in Education", undated; 308731 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Comments on High School Principals Association Report on Delinquency, 1952; 308732 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Communist Party, about, 1956, undated; 308733 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "Crisis in the Public Schools": Submissions and Correspondence, 1947; 308734 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "Crisis in the Public Schools": Various Editions, 1947; 308735 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "Cuban Revolution" (Incomplete), 1960; 308736 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Democracy and School Administration from the Teacher's Point of View", undated; 308737 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "Dictatorship of the Banks", 1932; 308738 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "Dictatorship of the Banks": Drafts and Research, [1932]; 308739 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - "Do You Know What Goes on at School?": on the Atlantic City Case of Rolston Gaiter, undated; 308740 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Editorials and President's Columns, 1938-1939; 308741 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Editorials and President's Columns, 1940-1941; 308742 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Editorials and President's Columns, 1942; 308743 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Editorials and President's Columns, 1943; 308744 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Editorials and President's Columns, 1944; 308745 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Editorials and President's Columns, 1945-1946; 308746 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Editorials and President's Columns, undated; 308747 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Educational Issues: Various, 1943-1948, 1951-1957, undated; 308748 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Educational Policy": Various Editions, 1955; 308749 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - "Enemies of the Public Schools", 1951; 308750 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - "Fascist Trend in American Universities", [1953]; 308751 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Federal Aid to Schools: Various, 1943-1947, undated; 308752 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Fight for Equal Pay in the South", 1948; 308753 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - "Free Press: An Absolute Necessity!", undated; 308754 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "Free Public School" (2), 1939, 1945; 308755 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - "Hearst the Arch-Enemy of Liberty": Testimony, 1936; 308756 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "Hitlerism in the Schools of France and Holland...", undated; 308757 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - "In Honor of Bella Dodd", [1944]; 308758 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "Influences for Peace in 1938", 308759 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "Issues in Spain and China", undated; 308760 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Ives Loyalty Oath, about, undated; 308761 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "Jeffersonian Democracy in 1943", 308766 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Lectures on Education: Outlines and Correspondence, 1954, 1958; 308767 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Letters: Cold War, 1959, 1961; 308768 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Letters: End the Korean War, 1951; 308769 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Letters: Various Pending Bills, 1958; 308770 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Letters to the Editor: Various, 1932-1951; 308771 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Letters to the Editor: Various, 1952-1962, undated; 308772 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "Our Interest in the War in Spain", 1936, 1938; 308773 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Press Releases: Various, 1939-1945; 308774 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - "Program of the Teachers Union" (2), undated; 308775 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Progressive Education, 1952, 1955; 308776 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - The Public Record: Hendley Contributions, 1948; 308777 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Rationale for Joining State, County and Municipal Workers (CIO): Draft and Outline, [1943]; 308778 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - "The Resurgence of Barbarism in Germany", undated; 308779 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - "Retrenchment in Education in the Space Age!", 1958; 308780 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - "A Review of a Course in Intellectual History" (Incomplete), 1914; 308781 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Right to Strike, 1947-1948; 308782 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - "Role of the Modern Teacher in Society", 1936; 308783 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - "Rose Riegger", 1955; 308784 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - "Schools for Fascism", 1948; 308785 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - "Schoolteachers' Strike", [1960]; 308786 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Smith Act, about, 1951; 312794 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - "Socialism in the United States", Aug 14, 1957; 312797 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - "Socialism in the United States": Early Versions, Apr 1957-Aug 1957; 308789 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - "Some Plain Talk about Reading", 1959; 308790 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Speeches: Various, 1935-1955, undated; 308791 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - "Statement to the Executive Council of the American Federation of Teachers", 1941; 308792 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - "Subversive Education Bill - S717" from The Protestant, June-July 1945, 308793 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - "Teachers and the CIO", 1948; 308794 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - "Teachers and the Freedom of Teaching", undated; 308795 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Teachers and the Labor Movement, 1936, 1939, undated; 308796 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Teachers' Salaries: Various, 1932, undated; 308797 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Teachers Union, Local 5: Various, 1935-1942, undated; 308798 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Teachers Union Pleads Guilty (bulletin), 1940; 308799 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Teachers' Workload, 1950; 308800 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Timone Resolution: Brief and Letter Writing Campaign, 1950; 308801 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - "To the Guild Strikers of the Brooklyn Bridge", undated; 308802 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - " Union Pleads on Behalf of the Unemployed Teachers", 1932; 308818 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "Unionism in the Educational Field" in The Social Frontier Vol. V, No. 45, May 1939; 308819 (Box 4, Folder 2)